Guide to the Morse Family Papers: William Reginald and Anne Crosse Kinney Morse
Yale University Divinity School Library
Morse Family Papers: William Reginald and Anne Crosse Morse
1909-1940
RG 265
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(5 boxes)
Medical missionary William Reginald Morse and his wife Anne (Anna) Crosse Kinney Morse served under the American Baptist Foreign Mission Society in China from 1909 to 1937. Substantive correspondence describes the daily life and work of the Morses, their travels, medical practice and education in China, and the turbulent political and social situation in China during this era. The Morses were based primarily Chengdu, Sichuan Province and at the West China Union University.
Morse, William R. (William Reginald), 1874-1939
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in cooperation with the Harvey Cushing/John Hay Medical Library of Yale University in 2014.
Associated Materials
The Morse Family Papers acquired by Yale in 2014 have been divided into two sections. The Morse Family Papers: William Reginald Morse and Anna Crosse Kinney Morse are held by the Yale Divinity Library while the Morse Family Papers: Marjorie Morse and Photographs are held by the Medical Historical Library.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. William Reginald Morse (1874-1939) was born August 30, 1874 in Lawrencetown, Nova Scotia, Canada, the son of Ellen Marry Fitch and Leander Rupert Morse. He received his medical degree from McGill University in 1902 and later did postgraduate work at Harvard University, Johns Hopkins University, and the University College of London, receiving a B.A., M.D., C.M, F.A.C.S., L.L.D, and F.R.G.S.
Dr. Morse practiced medicine in Rhode Island and Nova Scotia before being appointed in 1909 as medical missionary to China serving under the American Baptist Foreign Mission Society with his wife, Anna Crosse Kinney Morse (1875-1951), whom he had married in 1903. The Morses had one daughter, Marjorie, born in 1913.
Upon arrival in China the Morses traveled to Sichuan Province, West China, where Dr. Morse worked at a small missionary hospital for a few years. In 1914 Morse was sent to the provincial capital, Chengdu, where he helped found a medical school at West China Union University, an institution supported by various Protestant mission agencies. He was elected as Dean of the WCUU Medical School in 1919, Director of the College of Medicine and Dentistry in 1935, and was Professor of Anatomy and Surgery at West China Union University until his retirement in 1937. Dr. Morse also held positions at the Baptist College, and the Methodist Hospital in Chengdu. He served at the Hankow International Hospital during the revolution of 1911-1912 and at Lingnan University in Canton from 1927 to 1928.
In addition to his medical practice, Morse published five works relating to the history and practice of medicine in China and Tibet, including "The Practices and Principles of Chinese Medicine" and "A Memorandum on the Chinese Procedure of Acupuncture" in 1926. His major work was "The Three Crosses In The Purple Mists;: An Adventure In Medical Education Under The Eaves Of The Roof Of The World", published in 1928. Morse also did research and writing in the field of anthropology, publishing, for example an article titled "Schedule of Physical Anthropological Measurements and Observations on Ten Ethnic Groups of Szechwan Province, West China" in the Journal of the West China Border Research Society in 1937. Morse was the first president of the West China Border Research Society, and did much to maintain interest in its growth and development. He served as a research associate at the Peabody Museum at Harvard University in 1930-1931.
Dr. Morse passed away in the United States in November 1939.
Scope and Contents
This collection provides valuable documentation of the life and work of medical missionary William Reginald Morse and his wife Anne (Anna) Crosse Kinney Morse, who served under the American Baptist Foreign Mission Society in China from 1909 to 1937. Very detailed and substantive correspondence describes the daily life and work of the Morses, their travels, and the turbulent political and social situation in China during this era. Based primarily Chengdu, Sichuan Province and at the West China Union University, the Morses also spent time in Shanghai and other areas.
The Morse Family Papers acquired by Yale in 2014 have been divided into two sections. This collection at the Yale Divinity LIbrary includes papers of William Reginald Morse and Anna Crosse Kinney Morse while the Morse Family Papers: Marjorie Morse and Photographs are held by the Medical Historical Library.
The first series, Family Correspondence, includes many multi-paged letters from Dr. and Mrs. Morse to relatives in Nova Scotia and, after 1927, to their daughter Marjorie (born in 1913 in China) while she was attending an American high school, Wellesley College, and Yale Nursing School. These letters describe events such as the Morse family's 1909 initial long trip, traveling 1,800 miles inland from Shanghai, perilous travels by boat and by train, assistance to rural Chinese and military casualties caused by the fighting between Chinese warlords, the growth of Communism, and the Morses' religious, professional, and social interactions with the overall missionary and Chinese Christian community.
The second series, General Correspondence, includes primarily letters of condolence written to Anna Morse following the death of Dr. Morse in November 1939.
The third series, Writings and Notes, includes papers written by Dr. Morse including a medical report, two articles, and an essay regarding Chinese medicine and his medical work. This series also includes a book review of Morse's work "The Three Crosses in the Purple Mist" and several handwritten notes.
The fourth series, Personal Items and Memorabilia, includes biographical documentation regarding Dr. Morse, a friendship calendar with notes and photographs from supporters, and other memorabilia.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence
II. General Correspondence
III. Writings and Notes
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Missions -- China; Missions, Medical; Morse, William R. (William Reginald), 1874-1939; Morse, Anne Crosse Kinney; American Baptist Foreign Mission Society
- Family Correspondence, 1909-1937; Series I
  - W. R. Morse (WRM) and Anne Crosse Kinney Morse (ACM) to Mother and Rose en route to China, 1909 September-October (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    William Reginald Morse was known as "Reg" and Anne Crosse Kinney Morse was known as "Anna". Letters describe travel to China and exploration of new scenes and cities.
  - WRM to Mother from Shanghai, boat on Yangtze River, Ichang, 1909 November (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - WRM to Mother from boat on Yangtze River, Chungking (Chongqing), 1909 December (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Including description of operation of houseboat WRM is traveling on, landslides in the Yangtze River, Chinese language study, and WRM's medical work on passengers and workers aboard
  - WRM to Mother and Rose from boat on Yangtze River, Suifu (Yibin), 1910 January (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Including description of treatment of patients along the way to Suifu, arrival in Suifu, and the beginning of WRM's Chinese language study.
  - ACM to Mother and Rose from Chungking, 1910 January-October (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Arrival in China, plans for house.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, 1910 February (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Descriptions of Chinese people, homes, customs, and WRM's anxiety to learn the Chinese language and begin hospital work.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, 1910 March-April (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Including description of WRM and ACM's move into new house, Chinese customs (such as clothing, women's bound feet, and ancestral worship), and WRM's visit to his teacher's home.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, Chungking summer bungalow, 1910 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
    WRM's visits to patients, learning of Chinese medical remedies, and move to summer bungalow.
  - WRM to Mother from Chungking summer bungalow, 1910 June (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Severe storm damage to bungalows, Chinese wedding and feasts, and continuation of language study.
  - WRM to Mother and Walter from Chungking, Ichang, 1910 July (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Weather in China (overwhelming heat and insects), WRM's attendance at a childbirth, WRM and ACM's 26-day travel from Chungking to Ichang.
  - WRM to Mother and Lew from Chungking, 1910 August (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Death and funeral of a Chinese Christian evangelist: the transportation of his body to his home, Chinese ancestor worship in graveyard, and Chinese feast.
  - WRM to Mother from Chungking, Suifu, 1910 September (Box 1, Folder 12)
    WRM and ACM move back to Suifu from summer bungalow in Chungking, visit a wildlife park and salt mine.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, boat on Yangtze River, Chungking, 1910 October (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes description of the failing health of fellow missionary Dr. Lewis, WRM's escort of Lewis' family to Chungking, and WRM's visits to Chinese hospitals and British gunboat.
  - WRM to Mother from boat on Yangtze River, Ichang, Suifu, 1910 November-December (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Two-week return trip by houseboat to Suifu, the one-year anniversary of WRM's "active service" in China, river trip with a missionary and native evangelist, and return to Suifu.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, Yachow, 1911 January (Box 1, Folder 15)
    WRM and ACM on 10-day trip to Yachow for a conference; description of Chinese hotels and travel on river, and Chinese New Year customs.
  - WRM to Mother from Yachow, Chengtu (Chengdu), boat on Chengtu River, 1911 February (Box 1, Folder 16)
    WRM meeting with other missionaries, talk of some missions combining hospital work and religious work, and hospitality in Chengtu (Chengdu)
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, 1911 March-April (Box 1, Folder 17)
    WRM's return to Suifu, Chinese-language study and medical work, the death of the missionary Salquist from typhoid fever, and a shortage of workers.
  - ACM to Mother and Rose from Suifu, 1911 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Description of gifts that were sent to WRM and ACM from ACM's family, book recommendations for ACM's family, and life in the countryside of China.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, 1911 June (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Including regarding weather in China and problems with getting supplies.
  - WRM and ACM to Mother from Chungking summer bungalow, Kiating, 1911 July-August (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Daily life at summer bungalow in Chungking, trip to Kiating (Leshan), and the treatment of patients in Kiating.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, Chungking, 1911 September-October (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Including regarding government unrest and missionaries' removal to Chungking and Shanghai. WRM granted permission to stay in Chungking to work in hospitals, anxious to get back to Chengtu.
  - WRM to Mother and Walter from Chungking, Suifu, 1911 November (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Rebellion brings death to many Chinese, many missionaries forced to move but WRM able to stay in Chungking.
  - WRM and ACM to Mother from Ichang, Hankow (Wuhan), 1911 December (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Describes WRM's removal from Chungking station by British Consul, arrival in Hankow, and destruction of the city. WRM working with the Red Cross at Hankow International Hospital.
  - WRM to Mother from Hankow, Shanghai, 1912 January-February (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Including regarding the ending of WRM's work at Hankow International Hospital, temporary travel to Shanghai, and WRM turning down an offer to care for the wounded and famished at a hospital along the line of TienTsui Pakow Railway.
  - WRM and ACM to Mother from Shanghai, 1912 March-April (Box 1, Folder 25)
    WRM attending a language school in Shanghai. Missionaries receive appeal to volunteer for distribution food for famine relief; WRM joins this effort
  - WRM to Mother from Shanghai, Kuling, 1912 May-July (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Describes WRM leaving Shanghai, river trip to Kuling (Lushan District), and resort in Kuling.
  - WRM and ACM to Rose, Lew, and Mother from Shanghai, 1912 June-November (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Including regarding WRM and ACM's celebration of ninth anniversary of marriage and ACM's medical emergency and eventual recovery from kidney problem.
  - WRM to Mother from Kuling, boat on the Yangtze River, Chungking, 1912 August-September (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Including description of Anna's pregnancy and improvement of pregnancy complications, arrival in Chungking to help Dr. McCartney, and WRM's medical courses.
  - WRM to Mother from Ichang, boat on Yangtze River, Chungking, 1912 October (Box 1, Folder 29)
    WRM's travels from Ichang to Chungking (on the way to Suifu) and unsatisfactory conditions on boat.
  - WRM to Mother from boat on Yangtze River, Suifu, 1912 November-December (Box 1, Folder 30)
    WRM arrives in Suifu, reassembles servants, does necessary repairs on house and hospital, prepares to open a dispensary
  - WRM and ACM to Mother from Suifu, 1913 January-February (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Describes the continuation of hospital repairs, WRM's busy dispensary and interactions with dispensary patients, and the birth of daughter, Marjorie Morse, on February 24, 1913.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, 1913 March-April (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Including regarding WRM's work with patients in hospital and dispensary and an unusual request from the Cabinet of the New China Republic for prayers that virtuous men be elected and that government be established on a firm foundation.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, 1913 May-June (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Continued work at hospital and dispensary; WRM pleased by visit from the officers of a British gunboat in port.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, 1913 July-August (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Amidst political unrest and tension in China, ACM and Marjorie visit the "hills", WRM continues his hospital work.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, 1913 September-October (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Rebellion in area crushed for a time; hospital full.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, Chungking, 1913 November-December (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Describes WRM's happiness with his profession, growing fondness towards Marjorie, preparations for conference and thoughts about medical school
  - WRM to Mother from Chungking, 1914 January-March (Box 2, Folder 37)
    WRM turns 40 years old, satisfied with large amounts of work (over 300 operations). He expresses sadness and excitement towards leaving the hospital and going to medical school for new opportunities.
  - WRM to Mother from Chungking, Suifu, 1914 April-June (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Political unrest in China, WRM's treatment of patients who were victims of violence, ACM's illness and recovery, and the celebration of WRM and ACM's eleventh wedding anniversary.
  - WRM and ACM to Mother from Chungking, 1914 July-August (Box 2, Folder 39)
    WRM's continues his hospital work. Description of summer weather and a growing foreign population in China, and WRM's urge to volunteer as a doctor in the European war.
  - WRM and ACM to Mother from Suifu, Kiating, boat on the Fu River, Chengtu, 1914 September-October (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Including description of life in Suifu and the positive experiences of ACM and WRM, WRM waiting to hear back from the medical school, French and German soldiers going off to battle, and the Morse family settling in Chengtu.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, Kiating, 1914 November-December (Box 2, Folder 41)
    WRM recommended by the hospital Reference Committee for a teaching position at the West China Union University's Medical Department, the meeting of WRM and ACM's mothers in Brooklyn, and ACM starting to teach English to Chinese students.
  - WRM to Mother from Suifu, 1915 January-May (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Including regarding the start of WRM's work conference, Chinese tensions with Japan and the United States growing larger, and WRM's thoughts towards enlisting in the war in Europe.
  - WRM and ACM to Mother from Chengtu, Shanghai, 1915 July-November (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Includes description of WRM's travels in China, the physical changes of WRM and ACM since their arrival in China. WRM now the only foreign teacher in the West China Union University anatomy department.
  - ACM to Mother from Chengtu, 1920 August 25 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    ACM makes suggestions to mother about how to make life easier and describes Chinese nature, Chinese life, and her meeting at the Natural History Club.
  - ACM to Mother from Chengtu, 1921 June-August (Box 2, Folder 45)
    ACM's life at home and with friends while WRM is away on a trip, encloses letter written by a Mrs. Humphrey about WRM and his life in China.
  - ACM, WRM, and Marjorie Morse (MM) to Mother from Chengtu, 1922 January-December (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Describes events in the lives of ACM and MM and WRM's travel to Peking.
  - ACM and WRM to Mother and Elsie from Chengtu, Shanghai, 1923 January-December (Box 2, Folder 47)
    ACM worried about the amount of work that WRM is taking on, WRM's thoughts about leaving China for England, life with MM and work at the medical school; ACM teaching English and Drawing classes.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Shanghai, Canton, Hong Kong, 1927 May-November (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Describes the Morse family's move from Shanghai to Canton, daily hospital work and domestic life, MM beginning high school, WRM and ACM living in separate places, growing tensions between Chinese and foreign missionaries.
  - ACM to MM from Canton, Hong Kong, Shanghai, Seoul, Onseiri, 1928 January-June (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Describes the daily life events of WRM and ACM, WRM and ACM's travels and life events to and in Shanghai, Hong Kong, Seoul, and Onseiri.
  - WRM to MM from Canton, Shanghai, Seoul, Onseiri, 1928 January-June (Box 3, Folder 50)
    WRM writing a book about the history of the Chengdu Medical School, WRM and ACM's celebration of their twenty-fifth anniversary of marriage, continued medical work, and travels to Shanghai, Hong Kong, Seoul, and Onseiri.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Onseiri, Shanghai, Peking, Chungking, Chengtu, 1928 July-December (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Regarding WRM's book, political tensions and unrest in China, ACM's art exhibition opening, and the Morse family's travels and cultural experiences in Shanghai, Hong Kong, Peking, Seoul, and Onseiri.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Chengtu, Onseiri, train to Mukden, Shanghai, boat on the Yangtze River, Chungking, 1928 July-December (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Describes WRM and ACM's journey across China, Manchuria, and Korea, political tensions between the Chinese and the Japanese, and summer weather and daily events.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Chengtu, 1929 January-March (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Describes the passing of MM's Aunt Rose, severe fighting and assaults on steamers in China, MM's sixteenth birthday, WRM's work as a teacher in anatomy department, and his writing of a research paper about Chinese medicine.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Chengtu, 1929 April-June (Box 3, Folder 54)
    Including regarding publication and reviews for WRM's book "The Three Crosses in the Purple Mists", MM's college entrance examinations and induction into the National Honor Society, and WRM and ACM's recovery from bad health.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Beh Liu Din, Lifan, Chengtu, 1929 April-June (Box 3, Folder 55)
    Including regarding college recommendations for MM, WRM's travel to Lifan and life in Lifan, ACM teaching classes.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Chengtu, boat on the Min River, boat on the Yangtze River, Shanghai, Madras, 1929 October-December (Box 3, Folder 56)
    WRM reducing his time at hospitals and only taking on special medical cases, making preparations for travel back to America.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Madras, train to Benares, Bombay, boat on the Red Sea, 1930 January (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Including description of the people and customs of Madras and Bombay, dates and deadlines for arriving in Bombay and Egypt's Port Said, and WRM and ACM's excitement of getting home to MM.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from boat to Cairo, Cairo, the steamer S.S. Laurentic, Paris, London, 1930 February (Box 3, Folder 58)
    Describes a smallpox outbreak on WRM and ACM's ferry, sightseeing in Cairo, Egyptian people and customs, WRM getting asked to make a class speech at a college commencement
  - WRM and ACM to MM from London, 1930 March (Box 3, Folder 59)
    WRM visits London hospitals and the Medical Museum of the Royal College of Surgeons, travel in United Kingdom
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Chengtu, in U.S on train en route to Detroit, Chicago, Evanston, the Rockies, Ontario, S.S. Empress of Russia boat en route to Yokohama, Shanghai, 1931 June-October (Box 3, Folder 60)
    Describes WRM and ACM's happiness towards MM's success at school, MM starting at Wellesley College, WRM and ACM's railway travels to Detroit, Chicago, Vancouver, and Ontario to visit family and see scenery, MM starting college, and WRM and ACM's experiences in Japan.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Shanghai, boat on the Yangtze River, Chungking, boat on the Min River, Chengtu, 1931 October-December (Box 3, Folder 61)
    Including description of WRM's excitement to help people in medical need, meetings of the National Christian Council, effects of the flood of the Yangtze on Chinese homes and people, legal trouble with Chinese travel customs.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Chengtu, 1932 January-March (Box 3, Folder 62)
    Describes WRM's home and work experiences in Chengtu and at the West China Union University; WRM acting as the president of the West China Border Research Society and giving a lecture on acupuncture; special operations conducted at the hospital, and the tensions of the Sino-Japanese situation in Shanghai.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Chengtu, 1932 April-June (Box 3, Folder 63)
    Including regarding tensions between Chinese and Japanese; ACM teaching painting classes and WRM teaching at the university, meetings with foreign missionaries, and MM's college life and curriculum.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Beh Liu Tin, Chengtu, Canton, 1932 August-October (Box 3, Folder 64)
    Describes WRM's writing on anatomy and anthropological measurements, the outbreak of cholera in China, WRM and ACM's registration with the Chinese government, and WRM publishing work for the Peabody Museum at Harvard University.
  - WRM and ACM to MM from Chengtu, 1932 November-1933 January (Box 3, Folder 65)
    WRM has large amount of hospital work, including treatment of wounded soldiers.
  - WRM to MM from Chengtu, 1933 January-March (Box 4, Folder 66)
    Describes troubles arising in the United States, China, Europe, and Russia, WRM working on different reports and lectures, the illness and health improvement of WRM's colleague Dr. Lenox, and Chinese spring weather and seasonal customs.
  - WRM to MM from Chengtu, 1933 April-June (Box 4, Folder 67)
    Including regarding uprisings of Communism in the north-east and the eastern sections of the Szechuan province, MM's college examinations, China's election of a new president (Chang), the defeat in power of the warlord Liu Wen Hwei at Chengtu, and the temporary end of the Chinese Civil War.
  - WRM to MM from Chengtu, Seung Pan, Beh Lin Tin, 1933 July-August (Box 4, Folder 68)
    Describes the departure of the warlord Liu Wen Hwei from the city of Chengtu, the effects of the war-like conditions on normal citizens
  - WRM to MM from Beh Liu Tin, Chengtu, 1933 September-October (Box 4, Folder 69)
    Including regarding the beginning of MM's final undergraduate year at Wellesley College and her worries about her future, WRM's large classes in Anatomy and Surgery at the university, and the growth of Communism in China.